I am the daughter of a forger,
انا إبنة مزور
not just any forger ...
ولكن ليس أي مزور
When you hear the word "forger," you often understand "mercenary."
عندما تسمعون كلمة مزور .. سيجول في خاطركم على الفور الاحتيال
You understand "forged currency," "forged pictures."
فالتزوير يعني تزوير العملات او اللوحات الفنية
My father is no such man.
ولكن والدي ليس كذلك .
For 30 years of his life,
لمدة ثلاثين عاماً من حياته
he made false papers --
كان والدي يزور الاوراق الرسمية
never for himself, always for other people,
لا لنفسه بل للآخرين
and to come to the aid of the persecuted and the oppressed.
لقد غدا عون المضطهدين والمظلومين
Let me introduce him.
دعوني أعرفكم عليه
Here is my father at age 19.
هذا والدي في ال19 من عمره
It all began for him during World War II,
لقد بدأ العمل منذ الحرب العالمية الثانية
when at age 17 he found himself thrust
عندما كان في ال17 من عمره وجد نفسه في خضم
into a forged documents workshop.
عمل تزوير الوثائق
He quickly became the false papers expert of the Resistance.
وبسرعة غدا محترف التزوير للمقاومة
And it's not a banal story --
انها ليست قصة مبتذلة ..
after the liberation he continued
بعد التحرير استمر
to make false papers until the '70s.
في عمله في التزوير حتى ال70 من عمره
When I was a child
عندما كنت طفلة
I knew nothing about this, of course.
لم اكن أعلم شيئاً عن الامر
This is me in the middle making faces.
هذه أنا في منتصف الصورة .. أقوم بتصنع الحالات
I grew up in the Paris suburbs
لقد نشأت في ضواحي باريس
and I was the youngest of three children.
وكنت الاصغر بين 3 اطفال
I had a "normal" dad like everybody else,
لقد كان لدي والدٌ طبيعي كما الجميع
apart from the fact that he was 30 years older than ...
بغض النظر عن أنه أكبر مني ب30 عاماً
well, he was basically old enough to be my grandfather.
هو في الحقيقة أصح بأن يكون في مثابة جدي عوضاً عن والدي
Anyway, he was a photographer and a street educator,
على كُلٍ .. لقد كان مصوراً و معلماً
and he always taught us to obey the law very strictly.
ولقد حرص دوماً على ان يعلمنا اطاعة القوانين بصرامة
And, of course, he never talked about his past life
ولم يتحدث يوماً عن حياته السابقة
when he was a forger.
عندما كان مزوراً
There was, however, an incident I'm going to tell you about,
ولكن هناك حادثة اريد أن أخبركم عنها
that perhaps could have led me suspect something.
والتي جعلتني أبدأ قليلاً في الشك في الموضوع
I was in high school and got a bad grade,
لقد كنت في المدرسة الثانوية .. و كنت حينها قد حصلت على درجة سيئة
a rare event for me,
وكان حدوث ذلك نادراً
so I decided to hide it from my parents.
لذا قررت أن أخفي الموضوع عن والدي
In order to do that, I set out to forge their signature.
ولكي أقوم بذلك .. قررت أن اقوم بتزوير توقيعهما
I started working on my mother's signature,
وبدأت بمحاولة تزوير توقيع والدتي
because my father's is absolutely impossible to forge.
لان توقيع والدي كان من الاستحالة بمكان أن استطيع تزويره
So, I got working. I took some sheets of paper
فما حدث هو أنني أحضرت بعض الاوراق
and started practicing, practicing, practicing,
وبدأت أتدرب و أتدرب
until I reached what I thought was a steady hand,
حتى استطعت ان اعود يدي على تزوير التوقيع بدقة تامة
and went into action.
ومن ثم عمدت الى تزوير التوقيع
Later, while checking my school bag,
لاحقاً .. كانت والدتي تتاكد من حقيبتي
my mother got hold of my school assignment and immediately saw that the signature was forged.
فما حدث هو ان وقعت يدها على ورقة العلامات و ميزت على الفور توقيعها المزيف
She yelled at me like she never had before.
فعنفتني كما لم تعنفني من قبل
I went to hide in my bedroom, under the blankets,
فهربت لكي اختبأ في غرفة النوم اسفل الملايات
and then I waited for my father to come back from work
وثم انتظرت الى ان يعود والدي من العمل
with, one could say, much apprehension.
والذي كان بحسب ما أرى أكثر مرونة
I heard him come in.
وسمعته وهو يقترب نحو الغرفة
I remained under the blankets. He entered my room,
وبقيت أسفل الملايات .. ودخل غرفتي
sat on the corner of the bed,
وجلس على زاوية السرير
and he was silent, so I pulled the blanket from my head,
وجلس بصمت .. حتى اخرجت رأسي من أسفل الملايات
and when he saw me he started laughing.
وعندما نظر الى وجهي بدأ بالضحك
He was laughing so hard, he could not stop and he was holding my assignment in his hand.
وكان يضحك بشدة .. ولم يستطع ان يتوقف عن الضحك وكان ممسكاً بورقة علاماتي بيده
Then he said, "But really, Sarah, you could have worked harder! Can't you see it's really too small?"
ومن ثم قال " سارة ! ألم تستطيعي أن تهتمي أكثر في الموضوع .. ألا ترين أن التوقيع صغيرٌ جداً ؟ "
Indeed, it's rather small.
في الحقيقة كان صغيرٌ جداً
I was born in Algeria.
لقد ولدت في الجزائر
There I would hear people say my father was a "moudjahid"
وكنت اسمع الناس هناك يطلقون لقب " مجاهد " على والدي
and that means "fighter."
أي " مقاتل "
Later on, in France, I loved eavesdropping on grownups' conversations,
لاحقاً كنت استمتع بإلتنصت على احاديث الكبار
and I would hear all sorts of stories about my father's previous life,
وكنت اسمع جميع انواع القصص عن حياة والدي السابقة
especially that he had "done" World War II,
وخاصة ما قام به في الحرب العالمية الثانية
that he had "done" the Algerian war.
وما قام به في الحرب الجزائرية
And in my head I would be thinking that "doing" a war meant being a soldier.
وكان يجول في رأسي حينها ان المشاركة في الحرب تعني القتال المسلح
But knowing my father, and how he kept saying that he was a pacifist and non-violent,
ولكن عندما عرفت ما قام به والدي .. وكيف كان يصر على انه كان يقوم بعمل غير مسلح .. و عمل سلمي
I found it very hard to picture him with a helmet and gun.
كان من الصعب بمكان أن اتخيل والدي مع خوذة و بندقية
And indeed, I was very far from the mark.
وكان هذا الامرٌ بعيداً كل البعد عن إمكانية التصور
One day, while my father was working on a file
ذات يوم .. عندما كان والدي يعمل على ملفنا
for us to obtain French nationality,
المتعلق بالتقدم للجنسية الفرنسية
I happened to see some documents
صادف أن لمحت بعض المستندات
that caught my attention.
والتي استرعت انتباهي
These are real!
هل هذه وثائق حقيقية .. !
These are mine, I was born an Argentinean.
هذه لي ؟ أنا ولدت في الارجنتين ؟
But the document I happened to see
ولكن اهم تلك الوثائق التي ساعدتنا في
that would help us build a case for the authorities
تقديم طلبنا الى السلطات الفرنسية
was a document from the army
هي وثيقة من الجيش
that thanked my father for his work
تشكر والدي على خدمته
on behalf of the secret services.
في المخابرات العسكرية
And then, suddenly, I went "wow!"
فأُعجبت بهذا .. " يا إلهي ..
My father, a secret agent?
والدي عميل سري
It was very James Bond.
وكأنه جيمس بوند
I wanted to ask him questions, which he didn't answer.
فأخذته اسأله الكثير من الاسئلة .. والتي لم يجيب على أي منها
And later, I told myself that
فضمرت في نفسي
one day I would have to question him.
انني ذات يوم سوف أستفسر منه عن ذلك الامر
And then I became a mother and had a son,
ومن ثم غدوت أُماً لطفل
and finally decided it was time -- that he absolutely had to talk to us.
ومن ثم قررت انه قد حان الوقت لكي يخبرنا المزيد
I had become a mother
فقد كبرت وغدوت أُماً
and he was celebrating his 77th birthday,
وكان هو يحتفل بعيد ميلاده ال77
and suddenly I was very, very afraid.
وفجأة هلعت ..
I feared he'd go
هلعت من أن توافيه المنية
and take his silences with him,
وأن يأخذ صمته معه إلى الابد
and take his secrets with him.
وتختفي اسراره نهائياً
I managed to convince him that it was important for us,
واستطعت أن اقنعه ان هذا الامر ضروري لنا
but possibly also for other people
وربما لأشخاص آخرين أيضاً
that he shared his story.
إن هو شارك بقصته
He decided to tell it to me
فوافق على أن يخبرني
and I made a book,
وانا قمت بإصدار كتاب متعلق بذلك الخصوص
from which I'm going to read you some excerpts later.
وسوف اقص عليكم مقتطفات منه لاحقاً
So, his story. My father was born in Argentina.
حسناً .. قصة والدي هو أنه ولد في الارجنتين
His parents were of Russian descent.
وكان والديه من جذور روسية
The whole family came to settle in France in the '30s.
وإرتحالت العائلة لكي تستقر في فرنسا في الثلاثينات
His parents were Jewish, Russian and above all, very poor.
وكان والديه يهوديان .. وفقيران جداً
So at the age of 14 my father had to work.
و في عمر ال14 اضطر والدي للعمل
And with his only diploma,
وكان مؤهله العلمي الوحيد
his primary education certificate,
شهادته الإبتدائية
he found himself working at a dyer - dry cleaner.
فوجد له وظيفة في مصبغة أقمشة
That's where he discovered something totally magical,
والتي إكتشف بها شيئاً سحرياً
and when he talks about it, it's fascinating --
وعندما شرح لي الامر كان مبهراً ..
it's the magic of dyeing chemistry.
انها العملية السحرية للصبغ
During that time the war was happening
واثناء فترة الحرب
and his mother was killed when he was 15.
توفيت والدته عندما كان بلغ ال 15 من عمره
This coincided with the time when
وكان هذا متواكباً
he threw himself body and soul into chemistry
مع انغماسه قلباً وقالباً في الكيمياء
because it was the only consolation for his sadness.
فقد كانت عزائه الوحيد لأحزانه
All day he would ask many questions to his boss
وكان يقضي طيلة اليوم يطرح الاسئلة لمديره
to learn, to accumulate more and more knowledge,
لكي يتعلم ويكتسب المزيد من الخبرات
and at night, when no one was looking,
وفي الليل عندما يرحل الجميع
he'd put his experience to practice.
كان يقوم بالتجارب وحده
He was mostly interested in ink bleaching.
وكان اهتمامه الرئيسي بتبيض الحبر
All this to tell you
وهذه القصة كانت البداية
that if my father became a forger, actually,
في مسيرته في أن يصبح مزوراً
it was almost by accident.
في الحقيقة كان الامر صدفة
His family was Jewish, so they were hounded.
كانت عائلته يهودية .. وكانت مطاردة
Finally they were all arrested and taken to the Drancy camp
في النهاية تم اعتقالهم و سوقهم الى معتقل دارنسي
and they managed to get out at the last minute thanks to their Argentinean papers.
واستطاعوا ان يخرجوا من هناك في اللحظة الاخيرة بسبب الاوراق الارجنتينية
Well, they were out,
وعندما خرجوا ..
but they were always in danger. The big "Jew" stamp was still on their papers.
استمر الخطر بملاحقتهم .. فالختم اليهودي كان يتربع في منتصف اوراقهم الرسمية
It was my grandfather who decided they needed false documents.
فقرر جدي انه يجب ان يسعوا الى الحصول على اوراق مزورة
My father had been instilled with such respect for the law
وكان حينها والدي يكن احتراماً كبيراً للقانون بسبب الصفات التي غرسها به والده
that although he was being persecuted,
ورغم انه كان مطارد ..
he'd never thought of false papers.
الا انه لم يفكر على الاطلاق بتزوير الوثائق
But it was he who went to meet a man from the Resistance.
ولكنه هو من ذهب لمقابلة الوسيط من قبل المقاومة
In those times documents had hard covers,
في تلك الاثناء كانت الأوراق مغلفة غلاف متين
they were filled in by hand,
وكانت تعبىء بواسطة اليد
and they stated your job.
وكانت توضح طبيعة العمل
In order to survive, he needed
ولكي ينجو من الخطر .. كان يجب ان يكون الشخص عاملاً منتجاً
to be working. He asked the man
وقد طلب حينها من الوسيط
to write "dyer."
ان يكتب مهنة " عامل صباغة "
Suddenly the man looked very, very interested.
فنظر إليه الرجل بعين فضولية
As a "dyer," do you know how to bleach ink marks?
وقال له .. " اتعني عامل مصبغة يستطيع ازلة بقع الحبر ؟ "
Of course he knew.
وحتماً كان هذا مجال والدي
And suddenly the man started explaining that
وفجأة اخذ يشرح له مشكلة
actually the whole Resistance had a huge problem:
كبيرة كانت تواجهها المقاومة حينها
even the top experts
وحتى اكبر مختصيها
could not manage to bleach an ink, called "indelible,"
وهي انهم لم يستطيعوا ازالة نوع من الحبر يدعى " انديليبل "
the "Waterman" blue ink.
حبر العلامة المائية الازرق
And my father immediately replied that he knew exactly
فرد والدي على الفور انه يعلم الطريقة الملائمة
how to bleach it.
لازالة ذلك الحبر
Now, of course, the man was very impressed with this young man of 17
لقد اعجب الوسيط بهذا الشاب ابن ال17 من العمر
who could immediately give him the formula, so he recruited him.
والذي استطاع على الفور اعطاءه معادلة كيميائية لمحلول يزيل ذلك الحبر .. فجنده على الفور
And actually, without knowing it, my father had invented something
وبدون أن يدري مالذي حدث فعلاً .. كان والدي قد اكتشف شيئاً
we can find in every schoolchild's pencil case:
موجود اليوم في حقيبة كل طالب مدرسة ..
the so-called "correction pen."
وهو ما يدعى ( الكوركتر - مزيل الحبر )
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But it was only the beginning.
ولكن كانت هذه البداية فحسب
That's my father.
هذا هو والدي
As soon as he got to the lab,
ما ان وصل الى المختبر
even though he was the youngest,
ورغم انه كان الاصغر
he immediately saw that there was a problem with the making of forged documents.
الا انه على الفور استطاع اكتشاف مشكلة في صناعة الاوراق المزورة
All the movements stopped at falsifying.
حيث كانت عملية التزوير لا تنفك تتوقف
But demand was ever-growing
بسبب الطلب الكبير عليها
and it was difficult to tamper with existing documents.
ونقص الاوراق الاصلية التي كانت تقوم عليها عملية التزوير
He told himself it was necessary to make them from scratch.
فقال لنفسه يجب ان نصنع الاوراق بأنفسنا من الصفر
He started a press. He started photoengraving.
فبدأ بصناعة الاوراق .. وماكينات الطبع
He started making rubber stamps.
والاختام
He started inventing all kind of things --
وقام بصناعة كل ما تتطلبه الوثيقة الرسمية
with some materials he invented a centrifuge using a bicycle wheel.
كانت بعض من المواد التي صنعها تعتمد على عجلات الدراجات الهوائية
Anyway, he had to do all this
في الحقيقة قام بكل ذلك
because he was completely obsessed with output.
وكان يقوم به لانه كان مهووساً بالنتائج المرجوة
He had made a simple calculation:
وخرج بمعادلة بسيطة تنص
In one hour he could make 30 forged documents.
على انه قادر على تزوير 30 وثيقة كل ساعة
If he slept one hour, 30 people would die.
وان نام ساعة واحدة وتاخر فيها عن العمل فسوف يموت 30 شخصاً
This sense of
وضمن هذا النسق
responsibility for other people's lives when he was just 17 --
كان يعمل من دافع المسؤولية تجاه الاخرين
and also his guilt for being a survivor,
ومن شعوره بالذنب لانه نجى و غيره لم ينجو
since he had escaped the camp when his friends had not --
عندما استطاع الخروج من المعتقل ولم يستطع اصدقائه ذلك
stayed with him all his life.
وذلك الشعور بالذنب لازمه طيلة حياته
And this is maybe what explains why, for 30 years,
وهذا يفسر السبب الذي جعله يستمر بالتزوير
he continued to make false papers
لمدة 30 عاماً لاحقة
at the expense of all kinds of sacrifices.
مغامراً بكل شيء
I'd like to talk about those sacrifices,
وسوف اخبركم بما ضحى به من اجل هذا ..
because there were many.
لان هناك الكثير مما قدمه
There were obviously financial sacrifices
فبداية كان يضحي بوضعه المادي
because he always refused to be paid.
لانه كان على الدوام يرفض أن يؤجر على الوثائق المزورة
To him, being paid would have meant being a mercenary.
فالنسبة له أن يؤجر على التزوير فهذا يعني احتيال و تصرف سيء
If he had accepted payment,
ان قبل أن يؤجر على ما يقوم به
he wouldn't be able to say "yes" or "no"
فسيفقد القدرة على القبول او الرفض فيما يخص الوثائق
depending on what he deemed a just or unjust cause.
حيث كان يقيم الوثائق ان كانت ستخدم عملية تزويرها الخير العام ام لا
So he was a photographer by day,
كان يعمل مصوراً في النهار
and a forger by night for 30 years.
ومزوراً في الليل طيلة ال30 عام
He was broke all of the time.
وكان مفلساً طيلة هذه الفترة
Then there were the emotional sacrifices:
وكان هناك التضحيات العاطفية
How can one live with a woman while having so many secrets?
فكيف يمكن لرجل أن يعيش مع إمرأة مع كل هذه الاسرار
How can one explain what one does at night in the lab, every single night?
كيف يمكن ان يفسر ما كان يقوم به في مخبره طيلة تلك الليالي
Of course, there was another kind of sacrifice
وكان هناك تضحية أخرى
involving his family that I understood much later.
متعلقة بنا نحن كعائلته والتي خبرتها لاحقا
One day my father introduced me to my sister.
ذات يوم عرفني والدي على أختي ..
He also explained to me that I had a brother, too,
وقد شرح لي لاحقاً .. انني أملك أخاً أيضاً
and the first time I saw them I must have been three or four,
وقد تعرفت عليهم اول مرة عندما كنت في الثالثة او الرابعة من العمر
and they were 30 years older than me.
وكان اقربهم لي في العمر يكبرني ب30 عاماً
They are both in their sixties now.
وهما الآن في الستينات من العمر
In order to write the book,
ولكي أكتب الكتاب
I asked my sister questions. I wanted to know who my father was,
طرحت الاسئلة على اختي لكي أعلم كيف كان والدي قبل أن أأتي إلى هذه الحياة
who was the father she had known.
ومن كيف تنظر اليه كأب
She explained that the father that she'd had
فقالت لي ..
would tell them he'd come and pick them up on Sunday to go for a walk.
انه كان يعدهم ان يأتي يوم الاحد لكي يأخذهم من أجل نزهة سير
They would get all dressed up and wait for him,
وكانوا يتأنقوا من اجل ذلك وينتظرونه
but he would almost never come.
ولكنه لم يكن يأتي
He'd say, "I'll call." He wouldn't call.
كان يعد بالقول أنه سيتصل بهم ليخبرهم عن احواله .. لكنه لا يتصل
And then he would not come.
ولا يأتي لزيارتهم
Then one day he totally disappeared.
وذات يوم إختفى تماماً
Time passed,
ومر وقت طويل
and they thought he had surely forgotten them,
فظنوا في البداية
at first.
انه حقاً كان قد نسيهم حينها
Then as time passed,
ومن ثم مر وقت طويل آخر
at the end of almost two years, they thought,
ربما نحو سنتين .. فخُيل لهم
"Well, perhaps our father has died."
انه ربما قد قٌتل
And then I understood
ومن ثم استوعبت ..
that asking my father so many questions
ان طرح الكثير من الاسئلة على والدي
was stirring up a whole past he probably didn't feel like talking about
سوف يحرك في نفسه ذكريات لا يريد ان يتحدث بها او ان يتذكرها
because it was painful.
لانها كانت مؤلمة
And while my half brother and sister thought they'd been abandoned,
وبينما كان يظن أخوتي غير الاشقاء انني تُركت للغرباء
orphaned,
ويُتمت
my father was making false papers.
كان والدي يصنع الأوراق المزيفة
And if he did not tell them, it was of course to protect them.
وحتماً لم يكن يخبرهم بذلك من أجل حمايتهم
After the liberation he made false papers
وبعد التحرير قام بصنع أوراق مزيفة
to allow the survivors of concentration camps to immigrate to Palestine
لكي يدفع بالناجين من مخيمات الاعتقال بالهجرة الى فلسطين
before the creation of Israel.
قبل ان تُقام دولة إسرائيل
And then, as he was a staunch anti-colonialist,
ومن ثم كان قد عُرف كمقاوم للإستعمار
he made false papers for Algerians during the Algerian war.
وكان يقوم بتزوير الاوراق للجزائرين اثناء الحرب الجزائرية
After the Algerian war,
وبعد الحرب الجزائرية
at the heart of the international resistance movements,
وفي خضم الحركة التحريرية العالمية
his name circulated
كان اسمه قد عُمم
and the whole world came knocking at his door.
وكان الجميع يلاحقه
In Africa there were countries fighting for their independence:
في افريقيا كان هناك 4 دول تحارب من اجل استقلالها
Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Angola.
غينيا . غينيا بيساو . انجولا
And then my father connected with Nelson Mandela's anti-apartheid party.
ومن ثم تواصل والدي مع حزب نيلسون مانديلا المناهض للعنصرية
He made false papers for persecuted black South Africans.
وقام بصنع أوراق رسمية مزورة للمضطهدين السود في جنوب افريقيا
There was also Latin America.
وعمل أيضاً في أمريكا اللاتينية
My father helped those who resisted dictatorships
وقد ساعد هؤلاء الذين حاربوا الديكتاتورية
in the Dominican Republic, Haiti,
في الدومنيك .. وهايتي
and then it was the turn of Brazil, Argentina, Venezuela, El Salvador, Nicaragua,
و من ثم جاء دور البرازيل و الارجنتين و فنزويلا والسلفدور و نيكاراغوا
Colombia, Peru, Uruguay, Chile and Mexico.
وكولومبيا و البيرو والاوروغواي و شيلي و المكسيك
Then there was the Vietnam War.
ومن ثم جاءت الحرب الفيتنامية
My father made false papers for the American deserters
فزور والدي الاوراق للفارين من الخدمة العسكرية الامريكية
who did not wish to take up arms against the Vietnamese.
الذين رفضوا رفع السلاح في وجه الفيتنامين
Europe was not spared either.
وحتماً أوروبا لم تكن بعيدة عن ذلك
My father made false papers for the dissidents
والدي زور الاوراق للمنشقين
against Franco in Spain, Salazar in Portugal,
عن فرانكوا في اسبانيا .. وسالازار في البرتغال
against the colonels' dictatorship in Greece,
و الديكتاتوريين في اليونان
and even in France.
وحتى في فرنسا
There, just once, it happened in May of 1968.
ربما لمرة واحدة فقط .. في شهر مايو من عام 1968
My father watched, benevolently, of course,
تابع والدي بالطبع
the demonstrations of the month of May,
المظاهرات التي جرت في شهر مايو
but his heart was elsewhere, and so was his time
ولكن قلبه كان في مكان آخر .. ووقته مخصص لشيء آخر
because he had over 15 countries to serve.
كان لديه 15 دولة تطلب خدماته
Once, though, he agreed to make false papers
في الحقيقة ذات مرة وافق على تزوير أوراق
for someone you might recognize.
لشخص ربما تميزونه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was much younger in those days,
لقد كان يافعاً في تلك الايام
and my father agreed to make false papers
ووافق والدي على ان يزور له الاوراق الرسمية
to enable him to come back and speak at a meeting.
لكي يستطيع ان يعود ويتحدث في الاجتماع
He told me that those false papers were the most media-relevant
واخبرني ان هذه الوثائق كانت لأغراض إعلامية
and the least useful he'd had to make in all his life.
وكانت تلك الاقل فائدة من تلكم التي قام بها
But, he agreed to do it,
ووافق على القيام بعملية التزوير تلك
even though Daniel Cohn-Bendit's life was not in danger,
رغم ان دانيل كوهن-بينديت لم تكن حياته في خطر
just because
إلا أنه رأى
it was a good opportunity
انها فرصة جيدة
to mock the authorities,
للإستهزاء بالسلطات
and to show them that there's nothing more porous than borders --
ولكي يريهم انه لا يوجد اسهل من التسلل عبر الحدود
and that ideas have no borders.
وان الافكار لا حدود لها
All my childhood,
كل فترة طفولتي
while my friends' dads would tell them Grimm's fairy tales,
عندما كانت صديقاتي تسمع قصص جرائم الخرافية من آبائهن
my father would tell me stories about very unassuming heroes
كان والدي يقص لي قصص عن أبطال مغمورين
with unshakeable utopias
بمبادىء صلبة
who managed to make miracles.
استطاعوا ان يصنعوا المعجزات
And those heroes did not need an army behind them.
دون اي حاجة لرفع السلاح او وقوف الجيش معهم
Anyhow, nobody would have followed them,
ودون اي حاجة لوجود اتباع او مريدين
except for a handful [of] men and women of conviction and courage.
فقط كل ما كانوا يملكه هؤلاء الرجل وتلكم النسوة هو الشجاعة والاصرار
I understood much later
ولقد استوعبت لاحقاً
that actually it was his own story my father would tell me to get me to sleep.
ان والدي كان يقص علي قصته هو
I asked him whether, considering the sacrifices he had to make,
وقد سئلته ذات يوم انه وبالنظر الى كل تلك التضحيات التي قدمتها
he ever had any regrets.
هل تشعر بالندم على شيء ما
He said no.
اجابني بالنفي
He told me that he would have been unable
وقال لي انه لم يكن بمقدوره
to witness or submit to injustice without doing anything.
ان يشاهد او يعلم بالظلم دون ان يتصرف حيال ذلك
He was persuaded, and he's still convinced
وكان مقتنعاً .. وبقي كذلك
that another world is possible --
ان وجود عالم جديد
a world where no one would ever need a forger.
لا يحتاج لمزورين هو أمرٌ ممكن ..
He's still dreaming about it.
مازال يحلم بذلك
My father
والدي
is here in the room today.
هنا اليوم في هذه الغرفة
His name is Adolfo Kaminsky and I'm going to ask him to stand up.
واسمه " أدولفوا كامينسكي " وسوف اطلب منه الوقوف
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شُكراً لكم